Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
- Series V. Correspondence to and from Clairouin 1947-1977
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, January 29, 1974 to May 7, 1974. (Box 8, Folder 33)
    15 TL, in English, to VéN (14), from Garlick & Hoffman (1). Mostly regarding various contractual matters, especially the contract with Fayard for Transparent Things, situation in Brazil with Dr. Bloch and Abril, Folio edition of The Defense, and contract with Gallimard for King, Queen, Knave. Attempts to arrange a meeting between the Nabokovs and Fayard (either Orengo, or Hell and de Fallois) and/or the drop-off of the Ada translation, and asks for (and receives) a copy of the Andrew Field bibliography. With autograph record of telephone conversation (3.12.74) noting that VN is unable to receive de Fallois and Hell because he has 60 or so pages left to write of his novel.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, May 9, 1974 to October 11, 1974. (Box 8, Folder 34)
    12 TL, in English, to VéN, discussing various contractual and financial matters (especially the various foreign editions of Lolita the novel and VN's screenplay). Schébéko apologizes for her lax correspondence, and writes that she fully expects to be "sacked." She loves Look at the Harlequins! but deplores the "heinous problem of a translation, which will make it impossible to bring it out for several years I guess."
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, October 21, 1974 to December 26, 1974. (Box 8, Folder 35)
    4 TL, in English, to VéN, with 3 autograph notes. Mostly regarding various contractual matters (especially having to do with foreign editions of Lolita, the Lolita screenplay, French publication of Strong Opinions and Bend Sinister, and the placement of Look at the Harlequins!). A postal strike is not only making correspondence difficult, but preventing importation of American edition of Look at the Harlequins!; Schébéko is saddened by the deaths of several friends.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 1975 to September 16, 1975. (Box 8, Folder 36)
    8 TL, in English, to VéN, and 7 autograph notes (including at least 3 records of telephone conversations). Mostly re: various foreign editions of Lolita, VN's dealings with that "crook" Prins, an upcoming interview, and contracts with Fayard for Look at the Harlequins!, and two paperback editions of Ada. Schébéko's husband has just passed away.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, September 19, 1975 to November/December 1975. (Box 8, Folder 37)
    8 TL, in French and English, to VéN, and 1 memorandum concerning a contract dispute between Grijalbo and Discolibro. Other letters discuss various accounting matters (especially re Lolita), an offer from Juilliard/Plon (now headed up by Bernard de Fallois) to publish all of VN's as yet untranslated works (with an annotation recording the Nabokovs' approval, communicated via telephone), and the transfer of rights to Dmitri Nabokov.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 1976 to April 2, 1976. (Box 8, Folder 38)
    5 TL, in English to VéN, with 2 autograph calculations and 1 autograph record of a telephone conversation. Mostly re: the contract with Juilliard, possible translators for the short stories Juilliard is to publish (wonders about the translator of a recent story that has appeared in the French Playboy, and the status of Fayard's editions of VN's works (Ada, Look at the Harlequins!, Transparent Things and Mary). Discusses various other small contractual matters. Schébéko tenders her semi-resignation, as she has lost all interest in agenting since her husband's death, no longer feels she can do her job well. Besides, she has "always thoughtthat you [Véra] are a far better agent than any I know" (2.12.76).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, April 8, 1976 to March 28, 1977. (Box 8, Folder 39)
    9 TL and 1 TLS (a postcard from Schébéko), in English, to VéN, with 1 autograph record of a telephone conversation. Mostly regarding various contractual matters (including a translator for VN's short stories, and the Grijalbo agreement). Schébéko wonders at the length of time is has taken for the copy of Playboy she sent to the Nabokovs to arrive (possibly, she suggests, the result of a mailman tempted by the magazine's contents).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, April 15, 1977 to June 16, 1977. (Box 8, Folder 40)
    6 TL, in English, to VéN (4) and Garlick & Hoffman (2), with 1 typed list of copyright holders, and 1 autograph record of a phone conversation with Véra (noting, among other things, that VN is in the hospital). Discusses tax matters, the Grijalbo-Bartrina mess, and a book club edition of Ada. Schébéko is closing down the agency on June 30.
  - Correspondence between Vera Nabokov and Clairouin, January 3 - January 31, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    17 letters and notes, including 4 TLS from Véra in English and French, discussing the rights of publication and translation of Lolita and Invitation to a beheading.
  - Correspondence to the Nabokovs from Clairouin, February 2 - February 24, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    12 TLS and TL copies in French regarding rights and contracts for translations of Lolita and other works.
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs and Clairouin, March 3 - March 27, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    11 letters and notes, including 3 TLS from Véra, regarding rights and translations of Lolita and other works
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs and Clairouin, April 2 - April 30, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    12 letters and one contract (4 TLS [3 from Véra, 1 from Constantine Santas] and 8 TL from Clairouin) regarding foreign rights and translations of Lolita.
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs and Clairouin, May 3 - May 28, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    17 letters, notes, and contracts (including 3 TLS by Véra) re: rights, permissions and translations of Lolita, Sebastian Knight, the Vane Sisters, Chambre Obscure, Musique, and other works.
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs and Clairouin, June 1 - June 30, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    23 letters, notes, and contracts (including 7 TLS by Véra) re: Lolita, Pnin, Spring in Fialta, the Vane Sisters, Invitation to a Beheading, and other works.
  - Correspondences between the Nabokovs Clairouin, and others, July 1 - July 31, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    21 letters and notes between the Nabokovs, Clairouin, Henri Monneray, Maurice Chapelan and Girodias (including 4 TLS by Véra) re: Chambre Obscure, Lolita, Pilgrim, and other works.
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs and Clairouin, August 1 - August 20, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    10 letters, notes, calculations, (including 2 TLS by Véra) and contract for the Grasset edition of Chambre Obscure and Lolita.
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs and Clairouin, September 4 - September 29, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    10 letters and statements (including 3 TLS by Véra) between the Nabokovs, Clairouin, and Steimatsky).
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs, Clairouin, and publishers, October 7 - October 30, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    17 letters, notes, contracts, and calculations (including 2 TLS by Véra) re: compensation for Lolita and other works.
  - Correspondence between the Nabokovs and Clairouin, November 6 - November 29, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    20 letters, contracts, and accounting sheets (including 5 TLS by Véra) re: Lolita and Chambre Obscure.
  - Correspondence between Véra Nabokov and Clairouin, December 4 - December 9, 1959. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    2 TL and 1 TLS between Véra and Clairouin.
- Series VI. Miscellaneous 1932-1976 (Correspondence, Publicity, Contracts, Statements)
  - Miscellanous correspondence, April 1, 1947 and September 24, 1965. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    2 autograph letters, one from P. Nicholas probably to Ergaz, and one from John-Marie Jammes to Vladimir VN, asking for a piece for a new literary magazine.
  - Miscellaneous items, undated. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    24 autograph items, mostly calculations, but also including records of telephone conversation, drafts of telegrams and letters, notes explaining or recording enclosures, postal forms indicating receipt of items or letters, etc. All concerning VN.
  - List of titles issued by Folio. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    List of titles issued by Folio. Dated by month (January through April) but not year (probably early 1970s).
  - Photograph of Vladimir Nabokov by Gertrude Fehr, ca. 1965. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous publicity material, 1969 to ca. 1973. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Two items: (1) Publicity material for the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark, on the letterhead of Woodfall Films. The film was directed by Tony Richardson, with a screenplay for Edward Bond, and starred Nicol Williamson, Anna Karina, Jean-Claude Druot, Sian Phillips and Peter Bowles (1969). (2) Publicity material for the French publication of Despair (ca. 1973), possibly for a dust jacket. Includes a description of the novel's plot, a biographical blurb, and a short extract from the novel.
  - Contracts, March 14, 1932 to October 30, 1961. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Contracts for Laughter in the Dark with Grasset (1932), Lolita with Olympia (1955) and Gallimard (1956), for Despair with Gallimard (1957), for "Visite d'un musée" with Preuves (1959), for "Visite au musée" with Le Club Français du Livre (1961). List of contracts thru November 1, 1960.
  - Contracts, April 23, 1972 to July 30, 1975. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Contracts for Lolita, Despair, Pnin, The Defense, with Gallimard (the paperback editions; 1972), and for Despair with Gallimard (1972), addenda to the contract with Grijalbo for Lolita (1974 and 1975), contracts with McGraw-Hill, Juilliard and Plon for the Juilliard/Plon editions of A Russian Beauty, VN's Dozen, Tyrants Destroyed, Bend Sinister, Strong Opinions and Glory (ca. 1976).
  - Contracts, ca. 1976. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Contracts with McGraw-Hill, Juilliard and Plon for the Juilliard/Plon editions of A Russian Beauty, VN's Dozen, Tyrants Destroyed, Bend Sinister, Strong Opinions and Glory (ca. 1976).
  - Royalty statements, December 31, 1957 to December 31, 1960. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    For Despair, Lolita, Sebastian Knight, and Invitation to a Beheading. Originally in folder.
  - Gallimard statements, June 31, 1961 to May 8, 1963. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    For Despair, Lolita, Sebastian Knight, Conclusive Evidence, Pnin, and Invitation to a Beheading. Originally in folder.
  - Gallimard statements, June 30, 1964. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    For The Defense, Despair, Lolita, Sebastian Knight, Pnin, Conclusive Evidence and Invitation to a Beheading. Originally in folder.
  - Gallimard statements, December 31, 196 to June 30, 1965. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Gallimard statements, June 30, 1965 to February 28, 1966. (Box 10, Folder 13)
    For The Defense, Despair, Lolita, Sebastian Knight, Pnin, Conclusive Evidence, Pale Fire and Invitation to a Beheading. Originally in folder.
  - Gallimard statements, June 30, 1966 to December 31, 1966. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Gallimard statements, June 30, 1967 to July 31, 1967. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Gallimard statements, December 31, 1967. (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Gallimard statements, June 30, 1968 to December 31, 1968. (Box 10, Folder 17)
    For The Defense, Despair, Lolita, Sebastian Knight, Pnin, Conclusive Evidence, Pale Fire, The Gift and Invitation to a Beheading. Originally in folder.
  - Gallimard statements, June 30, 1969. (Box 10, Folder 18)
    For The Defense, Despair, Lolita, Sebastian Knight, Pnin, Conclusive Evidence, Pale Fire, The Gift, The Eye and Invitation to a Beheading. Originally in folder.
  - Gallimard statements, December 31, 1969 to December 31, 1970. (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Gallimard statements, December 31, 1971 to December 31, 1973. (Box 10, Folder 20)
    For The Defense, Despair, Lolita, Sebastian Knight, Pnin, Conclusive Evidence, Pale Fire, The Gift, The Eye, King, Queen, Knave and Invitation to a Beheading. Originally in folder.
  - Gallimard statements, December 31, 1974. (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Gallimard statements, December 31, 1975. (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Typescript of translation for "Le nuage, le lac, le château," undated. (Box 10, Folder 23)
    Typescript of translation for "Le nuage, le lac, le château" by V. Sikorski. Originally in yellow folder.